<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new and further narrative of the state of New-England being a continued account of the bloudy Indian-War, from March till August, 1676, giving a perfect relation of the several devastations, engagements, and transactions there : as also the great successes lately obtained against the barbarous Indians, the reducing of King Philip, and the killing of one of the queens, &amp;c. : together with a catalogue of the losses in the whole sustaining on either side since the said war began, as near as can be collected.</title>
            <author>N. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58606</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S120</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8787</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11904486</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11904486</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50660</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58606)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50660)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 509:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new and further narrative of the state of New-England being a continued account of the bloudy Indian-War, from March till August, 1676, giving a perfect relation of the several devastations, engagements, and transactions there : as also the great successes lately obtained against the barbarous Indians, the reducing of King Philip, and the killing of one of the queens, &amp;c. : together with a catalogue of the losses in the whole sustaining on either side since the said war began, as near as can be collected.</title>
                  <author>N. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.B. for Dorman Newman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: N.S.</note>
                  <note>"This is probably the narrative mentioned by Increase Mather (War with the Indians--Address to the Reader) as having been written by a 'Quaker in Road-Island.'" cf. Sabin.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>New England --  History --  Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50660:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50660:1"/>
            <p>A New and Further NARRATIVE Of the STATE of NEW-ENGLAND, BEING A Continued ACCOUNT of the Bloudy Indian-War, From <hi>March</hi> till <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1676.</p>
            <p>Giving a Perfect Relation of the Several Devaſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Engagements, and Tranſactions there; As alſo the Great Succeſſes Lately obtained againſt the Barbarous <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> The Reducing of King <hi>Philip,</hi> and the Killing of one of the Queens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with a Catalogue of the Loſſes in the whole, ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on either Side, ſince the ſaid War began, as near as can be be collected.</p>
            <p>Licenſed <hi>October</hi> 13. <hi>Roger L'Estrange.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               <head>C R</head>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. B.</hi> for <hi>Dorman Newman</hi> at the <hi>Kings Arms</hi> in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="definitions">
            <pb facs="tcp:50660:2"/>
            <p>For the better Underſtanding ſome <hi>Indian</hi> Words, which are neceſſarily uſed in the Following Narrative, the Reader is Deſired to take Notice,</p>
            <p>That a <hi>Swamp</hi> ſignifies a Mooriſh Place overgrown with Woods and Buſhes, but ſoft like a Quagmire or Iriſh Bogg, over which Horſe cannot at all, nor Engliſh Foot (without great difficulty) paſſe.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Sachem</hi> is a King, Prince, or Chief of an ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, over whom he is as an abſolute Monarch.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Squaw Sachem</hi> is a Princeſs or Queen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wigwams</hi> are <hi>Indian</hi> Huts or Houſes.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50660:2"/>
            <head>BOSTON, <hi>July</hi> 22. 1676.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving preſumed in Two former Letters to give you a faithfull Account, of the <hi>Original Occaſion</hi> (as near as I could Diſcover) and ſad <hi>Progreſſe</hi> of the Cruel Wars between us and our <hi>Barbarous Enemies,</hi> the <hi>Indians;</hi> I thought (having this other Opportunity) your <hi>Curioſity</hi> might <hi>expect,</hi> at leaſt (from that knowledge I have for many years had of your Courteous Diſpoſition) was aſſured your <hi>Good-nature</hi> would <hi>Pardon,</hi> the trouble, of a <hi>Further Relation</hi> of material Occurrences which have ſince happened amongſt us, the rather for that I remember my ſelf under the voluntary Obligation of a <hi>promiſe</hi> ſo to do.</p>
            <p>My laſt (which I hope you Received) was of the 9th of <hi>February,</hi> 1675/6: And ſeriouſly at that time my hand trembled, and my heart almoſt fainted, when my minde reflected on our preſent miſeries, and revolved for the future what might be the Iſſue of that <hi>Deluge</hi> of Calamity which threatned us; The Diſpenſation we lay under was <hi>Cloudy</hi> and affrighting, Freſh Meſſengers (like <hi>Jobs</hi> ſervants) howrly arriving to bring the Dolefull <hi>Tidings</hi> of New Maſſacres, Slaughters and <hi>Devaſtations</hi> committed by the <hi>Brutiſh Heathens;</hi> and certainly it cannot but deſerve both <hi>Wonder</hi> and <hi>Commiſeration,</hi> that theſe parts which were not many <hi>Moneths</hi> ſince hardly to be Parral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd for <hi>plenty</hi> and <hi>ſecurity,</hi> are now almoſt deſtroyed and laid waſte by the ſavage Cruelties of a <hi>bloody</hi> (and ſometimes <hi>deſpicable</hi>) Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; who are now become ſo well-furniſht with Arms and Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition (by the baſe treachery we fear of ſome of our Neighbours) ſo inſtructed in Diſcipline by Experience, and heightned in Pride by unexpected ſucceſſe, That unleſſe our God (whoſe <hi>tender mercies are over all his works</hi>) in compaſſion to the Engliſh Nation in this Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, wonderfully appear for our deliverance, nothing could be expected but an utter Deſolation; And of this his gracious dealing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, we have lately had ſeverall Inſtances, our Forces being crowned with ſucceſſe, and the Enemy put to flight, or ſo far divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50660:3"/>
and diſcouraged, that great Numbers have ſurrendred themſelves, when by our own ſtrength or outward Circumſtances we could leaſt expect it. But that I may ſet down things in ſome Method, I ſhall re-aſſume the Narritive of our Troubles, where I left off in my laſt Letter, and relate the moſt conſiderable Actions from that time, in the ſame Order as they happened.</p>
            <p>After that ſharp Eight on the 19. of <hi>November,</hi> whereof I formerly gave you the Particulars, our wounded men (in number about 150.) being dreſt, were ſent into <hi>Rhode-Island,</hi> as the beſt place for their Acommodation, where accordingly they were kindely received by the Governour, and others, only ſome churliſh Quakers were not free to entertain them, untill compelled by the Governour: Of ſo inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, peeviſh and untoward a diſpoſition are theſe <hi>Nabals,</hi> as not to Vouchſafe Civility to thoſe that had ventured their Lives, and received dangerous wounds in their defence. As for the <hi>Indians</hi> that ſurvived the battell, they forſook their New-built Fort, and that <hi>Swamp</hi> where the Fight hapned, and poſted themſelves in a <hi>Swamp</hi> twenty miles diſtant from thence; The Weather being extreme cold, and the ſnow ſo deep, that we could not for ſome time march in purſuit of them; yet ſtill kept Scouts abroad daily to obſerve their Motions, and thereby hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred them from coming to the Sea-ſide; killed and took Priſoners divers of them, as they were found ſtragling; and burnt great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of their <hi>Wigwams</hi> (or houſes:) And being re-inforced with ſome Additionall Forces from <hi>Boſton</hi> and <hi>Plimouth,</hi> together with a Bark la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with Proviſion, we reſolved to ſet upon them again with the firſt opportunity; And in order thereunto marched to <hi>Potuxit,</hi> where we underſtood, That two nights before the <hi>Indians</hi> had aſſaulted a Gentlemans Houſe about break of day with much Violence, and wounded Two men in it, ſtriving to Fire the Houſe ſeveral times, by tying Pine-ſplinters or long Poles in a Bunch fired, and held upon the Shingles; but thoſe within prevented that ſtratagem from taking effect, beat off the Aſſailants, and found one of them left dead upon the place; But the Out-houſes and Hay the <hi>Indians</hi> burnt, and drove a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all the ſheep and cattel: We marched after them with all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient expedition, and came to the <hi>Swamp,</hi> where they had been, but moſt of them were then fled, having by their Scouts diſcovered the advance of our men; yet our Horſe killed, and took many of them, following the purſuit, till our Horſes were tired, our men faint, and our victuals ſpent; Inſomuch that ſeveral horſes were killed and eaten, whereof the General (the worthy <hi>Joſiah Winſlow</hi> Eſquire, Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>New-London</hi>) eat his part, and in all as well hardſhips as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, was not wanting to encourage his men by his own valiant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: But finding it both vain and hazardous to march farther after this flying rabble of barbarous Heathens, who we heard were then got together, about 5000. men women and children, towards <hi>Quobage;</hi> Our Army left the Chace, and having placed a Gariſon of about Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty men, in Captain <hi>Smiths</hi> (a ſtrong) houſe, within four Miles of the <hi>Narraganſets</hi> Dwellings, marched homewards to <hi>Marleborough.</hi> and from
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50660:3"/>
thence to <hi>Boſton,</hi> where they were disbanded in <hi>December.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But upon this, the <hi>Indians</hi> began to appear abroad again as miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous as ever; For the very next week they ſet upon <hi>Lancaſter</hi> Town, killed ſeveral people, and carried away many priſoners; Such houſes as were fortified, defended themſelves, but the greateſt part of the Town they fired and plundered; and had deſtroyed the whole place, had not Captain <hi>Wadſworth</hi> upon hearing of the Guns come with great expedition from <hi>Sudbury,</hi> with a party to their relief; After this they cut off a farm-houſe near <hi>Sudbury,</hi> killed ſeven people in a barbarous manner, and carried ſome away captive: Three hundred of them ſet upon the Town of <hi>Maidesfield,</hi> and burnt at leaſt fifty Houſes, killed and took divers of the Inhabitants, being all ſurpriſed before they were aware: For the ſubtle <hi>Indians</hi> near day-break, came about the Houſes privately, and lay cloſe in the Fences; and as people came out of their Houſes, ſhot them down: Upon this the Governour of <hi>Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſachuſet</hi> ſent out about Five hundred or Six hundred men under the Conduct of Major <hi>Thomas Savadge</hi> and Captain <hi>Moſely,</hi> as next in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to him, who having intelligence by a girl that had made her eſcape, that the <hi>Indians</hi> were in Three Towns beyond <hi>Quoboge,</hi> march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thither, where they joyned Major <hi>Treat</hi> with the <hi>Connecticot</hi> Forces; but the Enemy were fled; only skulkingly out of the Woods, they ſhot one of Captain <hi>Moſeleys</hi> men, and wounded one or two more: But their main body being cloſely purſued, diſperſed and ran into <hi>Woods</hi> and <hi>Swamps,</hi> ſo that it was impoſſible for our men to come up with them, and therefore marched away for <hi>Hadley</hi> and <hi>Northampton,</hi> to ſecure them and the other Towns in thoſe parts, and by a ſpecial Providence came very ſeaſonably; For within two days after his Arrival, <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton</hi> (though fortified round) was aſſaulted, the Centinel ſurpriſed and ſlain, and the Enemy entred the Fortifications: Being ignorant (as it is ſuppoſed) of any Recruits newly come thither, but found ſuch warm entertainment, that though they had kindled their fire, they durſt not ſtay to roaſt their break-faſt, but were forced to fly with great confuſion; we having loſt only three men, and the Enemy above twenty, as was judged, though the number could not be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly known; it being their Cuſtome to carry off their dead always with them, if poſſible: The next day they appeared about a thouſand ſtrong, whereupon the Major drew out his Forces, and purſued them to their uſuall place of Rendevouz near <hi>Deerfield;</hi> But they would not abide his coming up with them, but fled diſperſedly into the Woods, where he was able to do little or no Execution upon them.</p>
            <p>The Councill of <hi>Boſton</hi> (to the great ſurprize of many people) refuſing to maintain the <hi>Narraganſet</hi> Garriſon, raiſed by the United Colonies, lodged as aforeſaid in Mr <hi>Smiths</hi> houſe, they having eat and deſtroyed what they could, quitted the ſaid Houſe, thoſe of the Soldiers that belonged to <hi>Connecticot</hi> hiring a Boat to tranſport them to <hi>Pawcatucke,</hi> fearing to March through the <hi>Narraganſet</hi> Countrey, and thoſe of the <hi>Maſſachuſets</hi> and <hi>Plimmouth</hi> went to <hi>Seacunicke;</hi> But
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50660:4"/>
the very next day after their Departure, the <hi>Indians</hi> came and burnt the ſaid <hi>Garriſon-houſe</hi> (one of the moſt <hi>delightfull</hi> ſeats in <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) and another houſe of the ſaid Capt. <hi>Smiths</hi> at <hi>Sawgaw,</hi> together with all the Houſes at <hi>Narraganſet;</hi> and the day following aſſaulted <hi>Warwick</hi> with ſo unhappy a ſucceſſe, that they burnt moſt of the Houſes there, and indeed ruined all but four, which during the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent danger were kept by their owners with their friends and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants as Garriſons; Out of which there was a ſally made with Twenty men, who with the loſſe of one of their number killed ten of the <hi>Indians,</hi> yet could not preſerve the reſt of the Town, nor hinder them from carrying from thence a Conſiderable booty of Cattel.</p>
            <p>The 14th of <hi>March</hi> the ſavage Enemy ſet upon a Conſiderble Town called <hi>Groughton,</hi> and burnt Major <hi>Wilberds</hi> Houſe firſt (who with his Family removed to <hi>Charls</hi> Town) and afterwards deſtroyed ſixty Five dwelling-houſes more there, leaving but ſix houſes ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the whole Town, which they likewiſe furiouſly attempted to ſet on fire; But being fortified with Arms and Men as Gariſons, they with their ſhot, killed ſeveral of the Enemy, and prevented ſo much of their deſigne; Nor do we hear that any perſon on our ſide was here either ſlain or taken captive; But the very next day two men co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from <hi>Malbury</hi> to <hi>Sudbury,</hi> were ſet upon in the Woods by a great Number of <hi>Indian Women,</hi> armed with Clubs, pieces of Swords, and the like, who by their numbers having over-maſtered the two poor Travellers, that had nothing but ſmall ſticks to defend themſelves with, beat out their brains, and cut off their privy members, which they carried away with them in triumph; ſo vain it is to expect any thing but the moſt barbarous uſages from ſuch a people amongſt whom the moſt milde and gentle ſex delight in cruelties, and have utterly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned at once the two proper Virtues of Womankinde, Pity and Modeſty.</p>
            <p>Their next Attempt (I mean of any conſiderable Body of the <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>) was upon a Town called <hi>Naſhaway,</hi> which they ſet fire to, and burnt down to the ground; There was little reſiſtance made here, people endeavouring rather to eſcape their Fury by flight then oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; and yet they killed many, burnt the Town down to the ground, and took no leſſe then five and fifty perſons into their merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Captivity: And that you may perceive the malicious hatred theſe Infidels have to Religion and Piety, it may be obſerved, how they endeavour to ſignalize their Cruelty, and gratifie their enraged ſpleen, chiefly on the promoters of it; For of theſe 55. Captives, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Towns Relations made up no leſſe then ſeventeen, <hi>viz.</hi> Mrs <hi>Rowlinſon</hi> the Miniſters Wife, and his three Children, and two Siſters of her own, with ſeven, and the other with four Children; As they were leading them away in this lamentable condition, one of the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters being big with childe, going into the Woods to be privately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, the <hi>Indians</hi> followed, and in a jeering manner, they would help her, and be her Midwives, and thereupon they barbarouſly ript
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50660:4"/>
up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and burnt the childe before her face, and then in a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull cruelty, to put her out of her pain, knockt her o'th head; There was a Report that they had forced Mrs <hi>Rowlinſon</hi> to marry the one-eyed <hi>Sachem,</hi> but it was ſoon contradicted; For being a very pious Woman, and of great Faith, the Lord wonderfully ſupported her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this affliction, ſo that ſhe appeared and behaved her ſelf amongſt them with ſo much courage and majeſtick gravity, that none durſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any violence to her, but on the contrary (in their rude manner) ſeemed to ſhew her great reſpect; But who can expreſſe the ſorrows of her Husband, the Miniſter, and his Brother, when returning from <hi>Boſton,</hi> preſently after the Engagement, they found all their Goods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, their Houſes laid in aſhes, and their dear Wives and Children thus miſerably captivated: This was a fit Scene for Faith and Patience to be exerciſed in; In ſuch a juncture of affairs a man had need have a God to go to for ſupport, and an Intereſt in Chriſt to yield him Conſolation: Mr <hi>Rowlinſon</hi> after much pains and trouble ranſomed his Wife for Twenty Pounds, and got her out of their hands, but his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and the reſt (if living) remain ſtill in that moſt Wretched Slavery.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time one Mr. <hi>Clarks</hi> Wife, Children, and all his Family at his Farm-houſe two miles from <hi>Plimouth,</hi> were ſurprized and killed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept one Boy, who was knockt down, and left for dead, but afterwards taken up and revived; The houſe they plundred of proviſion and goods to a great value, Eight compleat Arms, 30 <hi>l.</hi> of Powder, with an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable Quantity of Lead for Bullets, and 150 <hi>l.</hi> in ready money, The ſaid Mr. <hi>Clark</hi> himſelf narrowly eſcaping their Cruelty by being at that Inſtant at a Meeting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sunday</hi> the 26th of <hi>March</hi> was ſadly remarkable to us for the Tidings of a very deplorable diſaſter brought unto <hi>Boſton</hi> about 5 a Cloak that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon by a Poſt from <hi>Dedham, viz.</hi> That Captain <hi>Peirce</hi> ſcituate in <hi>Plim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> Colony, having Intelligence in his Garriſon at <hi>Seaconicke,</hi> that a Party of the Enemy lay near Mr. <hi>Blackſtones,</hi> went forth with 63 <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and 20 of the <hi>Cape Indians,</hi> (who had all along continued faithful, and joyned with them); and upon their march, diſcovered rambling in an obſcure woody place, 4 or 5. <hi>Indians,</hi> who in getting away from us hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as if they had been Lame or wounded; But our men had purſued them but a little way into the woods, before they found them to be only De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coys to draw them into their Ambuſcade; For on a ſudden, they diſcovered above 500 <hi>Indians,</hi> who in very good order furiouſly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacqued them, being as readily received by ours; So that the Fight began to be very fierce and dubious, and our men had made the Enemy begin to retreat, but ſo ſlowly, that it ſcarce deſerved that name; when a freſh company of about 400. <hi>Indians,</hi> came in, ſo that the Engliſh and their few <hi>Indian</hi> friends were quite ſurrounded, and beſet on every ſide; Yet they made a brave reſiſtance for above Two hours; During all which time, they did great execution upon the Enemy, whom they kept at a diſtance, and themſelves in order; For Captain <hi>Pierce</hi> caſt his 63. Engliſh and 20 <hi>Indians</hi> into a Ring, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50660:5"/>
fought back to back, and were double-double diſtance all in one Ring whilſt the <hi>Indians</hi> were as thick as they could ſtand Thirty deep: Over power'd with whoſe Numbers, the ſaid Captain, and 55. of his Engliſh, and ten of their <hi>Indian</hi> friends were ſlain upon the place; which in ſuch a Cauſe, and upon ſuch diſadvantages may certainly be ſtiled, <hi>The Bed of Honour:</hi> However they ſold their worthy Lives at a gallant rate; It being affirmed by thoſe few that (not without wonderfull difficulty, and many wounds) made their eſcape, that the <hi>Indians</hi> loſt as many Fighting men (not counting women and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren) in this Engagement, as were killed at the battle in the <hi>Swamp</hi> near <hi>Narraganſet,</hi> mentioned in our laſt Letter, which were gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally computed to be above Three hundred.</p>
            <p>The ſame day ſome Chriſtians going to a Meeting at <hi>Springfield</hi> with a ſmall Guard, were ambuſcaded by Eight <hi>Indians,</hi> and a man and woman ſlain; and the reſt (ſuppoſing the Enemies number to have been greater then it was, for in truth our men were twice as many, yet ſtruck with terrour, fled, and left two women and two Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to the Enemies mercy, whom they carried away captive, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſulting, that ſo few of them ſhould make ſo many Engliſh fly: Of this accident Major <hi>Savage</hi> at <hi>Hadly</hi> being immediatly advertiſed by a Poſt, ſent ſpecially on that occaſion, diſpatcht a Party of Horſe to purſue the Enemy, and the next morning found their Track, and ſoon after diſcovered them; who ſeeing our men approach, took the two poor Infants, and in the ſight both of their Mothers and our men, toſſed them up in the air, and daſht their brains out againſt the Rocks, and with their hackets knockt down the women, and forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with fled: The place being exceeding rocky and a <hi>Swamp</hi> juſt by, our horſe could not follow them, and on foot were not able to overtake them; So that the bloudy Villains for the preſent eſcaped deſerved vengeance; Yet it pleaſed God, that both the women revived, and being come again to their underſtanding, one of them declared, that ſhe knew every particular perſon of theſe Eight <hi>Indians,</hi> and that they adviſed them to put all the men they could light upon to death, but to ſave as many women and houſes as they could for them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On Tueſday following, the barbarous Infidels deſtroied ſixty and ſix Houſes, beſides Barns and Buildings in <hi>Seaconicke;</hi> but we do not hear of any perſon there ſlain: On <hi>Wedneſday</hi> they ſtormed <hi>Providence,</hi> and conſumed the greateſt part of the Houſes, but without taking away the life of any perſon, except one <hi>Wright,</hi> of whom it is reported, That he was a man of a ſingular and ſordid humour; of great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the Scriptures, but of no particular profeſſed ſect or perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; one that derided Watches, Fortifications, and all publick en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours and adminiſtrations for the common ſafety; Inſomuch that after all alarms round about, he refuſed to bring in any of his Goods (which were of conſiderable value) or to ſhelter himſelf in any Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, but preſumed he ſhould be ſafe in his own houſe, where the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy found and butchered him: It is further credibly related con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him, that he had a ſtrange confidence or rather conceit, that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50660:5"/>
whileſt he held his Bible in his hand, he looked upon himſelf as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure from all kinde of violence; and that the Enemy finding him in that poſture, deriding his groundleſſe apprehenſion or folly therein, ript him open, and put his Bible in his belly.</p>
            <p>But indeed the reaſon that the Inhabitants of the Towns of <hi>Seaconick</hi> and <hi>Providence</hi> generally eſcaped with their lives, is not to be attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to any compaſſion or good-nature of the <hi>Indians,</hi> (whoſe very mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are inhumane cruelties), but (next to Gods providence) to their own prudence in avoiding their fury, when they found themſelves too weak and unable to reſiſt it, by a timely Flight into <hi>Rhode-Iſland,</hi> which now became the common <hi>Zoar,</hi> or place of Refuge for the Diſtreſſed; yet ſome remained till their coming to deſtroy the ſaid Towns; as in particular Mr <hi>Williams</hi> at <hi>Providence,</hi> who knowing ſeveral of the chief <hi>Indians</hi> that came to fire that Town, diſcourſed with them a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable time, who pretended, their greateſt quarrel was againſt <hi>Plim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth;</hi> and as for what they attempted againſt the other Colonies, they were conſtrained to it, by the ſpoil that was done them at <hi>Narraganſet;</hi> They told him, that when Captain <hi>Pierce</hi> engaged them near Mr. <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones,</hi> they were bound for <hi>Plimouth;</hi> They gloried much in their ſucceſſe, promiſing themſelves the Conqueſt of the whole Country, and root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of all the Engliſh: Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> reproved their confidence, minded them of their Cruelties, and told them, that the <hi>Bay, viz. Boſton,</hi> could yet ſpare Ten thouſand men; and if they ſhould deſtroy all them, yet it was not to be doubted, but our King would ſend as many every year from <hi>Old England,</hi> rather then they ſhould ſhare the Countrey; they anſwered proudly, That they ſhould be ready for them, or to that effect, but told Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> that he was a good man, and had been kinde to them formerly, and therefore they would not hurt him.</p>
            <p>About the latter end of <hi>March,</hi> came advice from <hi>New-York,</hi> That the <hi>Indians</hi> in a bravado had releaſed two Engliſh Captives, and ſent them down thither to give Information of what they had ſeen, which was, That being carried with a Party three days Journey towards the North Eaſt, from the place where King <hi>Philip</hi> lay (which was between thirty and fourty Engliſh miles from <hi>Albany;</hi> He came up to an <hi>Indian</hi> Rendevouz made by a mighty <hi>Sachem</hi> near <hi>Hoſſicke</hi>-River towards <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> where one of them told one and Twenty hundred men compleat, and the <hi>Indians</hi> themſelves drawing out into three ranks, that he might view them the better) made him tell them over three times, who he ſaid were generally well-armed with good fire-arms, and moſt of them young men, few ſo old as forty; And that amongſt them there were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 500. of thoſe with ſtraws about their noſes, commonly called <hi>French</hi>-Indians; That neither King <hi>Philip,</hi> nor that party, conſiſting of about four hundred, were then with them, and that the ſaid <hi>Philips</hi> own men were not above one hundred; himſelf being very ſickly, and having but little eſteem or authority amongſt them.</p>
            <p>One of the ſaid releaſed priſoners declared further, that from that ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devouz he returned with the reſt towards <hi>Albany,</hi> being afterwards given by the <hi>North-Indians</hi> to the <hi>Mahicanders</hi> or <hi>River-Indians</hi> (who have been
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50660:6"/>
always ſuſpected to be too kinde to thoſe bloody ones of the <hi>North;</hi>) And alſo affirms, that the ſaid <hi>North-Indians</hi> at the ſaid rendevouz in a vapour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing manner declared, that their intent was firſt to deſtroy <hi>Connecticot</hi> this Spring, then <hi>Boſton</hi> in the Harveſt, and afterwards the <hi>Dutch</hi> (meaning what the <hi>Dutch</hi> had here.)</p>
            <p>About the ſame time alſo, there was much diſcourſe and conſultation about a project for giving theſe Northern <hi>Indians</hi> that thus infeſted and haraſſed <hi>New-England,</hi> a diverſion, by engaging the <hi>Mohucks</hi> (another ſort of <hi>Indians,</hi> inhibiting towards <hi>New-York</hi> and formerly inveterate enemies to theſe) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ainſt them on the other ſide; and it was certainly reported, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>vernour of <hi>New-York,</hi> would upon requeſt and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable propoſalls freely make uſe of his intereſt amongſt that people (which is very great) for effecting ſo good a deſigne; Yea, the <hi>Pequod Sachem</hi> (who always has continued freindly and faithful to the Engliſh, venturing his men on all occaſions, who have done very good ſervice) ſeemed much to wonder, that we did not carry it on, affirming, that the ſaid <hi>Mohucks</hi> were the only perſons likely to put an end to the war, by hindring the Enemy from planting, and forcing them down upon us; but this counſell (for I know not what good reaſons of ſome amongſt us) was not thought fit (at leaſt for the preſent) to be ſo vigourouſly purſued as ſome expected: But to proceed with the Narrative.</p>
            <p>On the ſecond of <hi>April,</hi> Maj. <hi>Savage,</hi> Capt. <hi>Moſely,</hi> Capt. <hi>William Turner</hi> and Capt. <hi>Whitpoll</hi> with 300 men marched from <hi>Marleborow</hi> to <hi>Quoboge,</hi> where they had ordered the <hi>Connecticot</hi> Forces to attend their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and accordingly the parties being joined, endeavoured to finde out the Enemy and give them battel; But theſe Heathens being like wolves and other beaſts of prey, that commonly do their miſchiefs in the Night, or by ſtealth, durſt not come forth out of the woods and <hi>Swamps</hi> where they lay skulking in ſmall companies; being ſo light of foot, that they can run away when they liſt, and paſſe boggs, rocky mountains and thickets where we could by no means purſue them; only now and then we met with ſome ſtraglers before they were aware; and one time march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards <hi>Northampton,</hi> had a brisk diſpute with a ſmall party, who fell upon our rear, but we quickly repelled them, and killed about 20. in a hot purſuit after them, without the loſſe of one man on our ſide, and but one wounded.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time Maj. <hi>Palmer</hi> having been ſcouring the <hi>Narragan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets</hi> Country, brought in 30. of the Enemy, and 60. of <hi>Ninnicrofts</hi> people, which were about 30. fighting men, who delivered up themſelves to our protection; we kept their wives and children ſafely as hoſtages, and made the men go abroad with our parties, who did us great ſervice in clearing the woods; likewiſe the <hi>Pequods</hi> and <hi>Mohegins</hi> (who proved a good guard to <hi>New London, Norwich,</hi> and the Rivers mouth) brought in 27. of the Enemy and much plunder.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> the 6. <hi>John Winthrope</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> a member of the Royal Society, and Governour of <hi>Connecticot Colony,</hi> having like a faithfull patriot ſerved his Country, dyed at <hi>Boſton</hi> of a natural diſtemper after about 8. days ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and was there interred in his fathers Tomb, with an Univerſal la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, and all the Honours that our diſtreſſes and diſtractions would
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50660:6"/>
allow; And though it be uſually ſaid, <hi>Inter arma ſilent Muſae,</hi> yet could not all our martial confuſions wholly ſtrike our Muſes dumb upon ſo worthy an occaſion (enough to make our Countrey bathe it ſelf in tears, as it hath late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done in bloud) but they appeared in publique to pay a Funeral Tribute to his Honourable duſt, in a no leſſe ingenious then paſſionate and mournfull Elegy upon him, Printed here at <hi>Boſton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next day the Governour intended to have marched out with about 300 <hi>Engliſh</hi> of his own Colony, and 50 <hi>Cape-Indians,</hi> and all things were in a readineſs accordingly, but not being ſupplied with any aſſiſtance from us, he wanted Soldiers to ſecure his own Towns if they ſhould be attacqued ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly by the <hi>Indians</hi> (who lie in wait for ſuch opportunities) during his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and therefore was forced to let fall his deſigne, and continue at home.</p>
            <p>The 11. of <hi>April</hi> Cap. <hi>Deniſon</hi> with an 100. <hi>Engliſh</hi> Volunteers belonging to <hi>Connecticot</hi> Colony and as many <hi>Indians,</hi> of whom ſome were <hi>Mohegins,</hi> ſome <hi>Pequods,</hi> and ſome of <hi>Ninnicrofts</hi> men that had revolted from him; the ſaid friendly <hi>Indians</hi> being commanded by the young <hi>Sachem Unkus</hi> whoſe Father (the only Chriſtian <hi>Sagamore</hi>) hath during all this War continued faithful; Upon their March, ranging the <hi>Narraganſet</hi> Countrey near <hi>Potuxit,</hi> they fell upon a Party of the Enemy, Commanded by that famous but very bloudy and cruel <hi>Sachem, Quononſhot,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Myantonomy,</hi> whom the <hi>Engliſh</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly preſented with a rich Lac't Coat; they fought very obſtinately a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable time, but at laſt our men with very ſmall loſſe obtained the victory, killed above 50 of the Enemy on the place, and took 40. more alive, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt that inſolent <hi>Sachem Myantonomy</hi> himſelf, together with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Sachem,</hi> and ſeveral other of his chief Counſellors and friends; The ſaid <hi>Myantonomys</hi> carriage was ſtrangely proud and lofty after he was taken; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing examined why he did foment that War which would certainly be the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of him and all the Heathen <hi>Indians</hi> in the country, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He would make no other reply to any Interrogatories, but this; That he was born a Prince, and if Princes came to ſpeak with him he would anſwer, but none preſent being ſuch, he thought himſelf obliged in honour to hold his tongue, and not hold diſcourſe with ſuch perſons below his birth and quallity; He told them, he wiſht rather to die then to continue under confinement; that all he deſired was not to be tortured, but preſently put to death, which he requeſted might be done by young <hi>Unkus</hi> that aided us, as acknowledging him his fellow Prince, yet withall threatned, he had 2000. men would revenge his death ſeverely; wherefore our Forces fearing an eſcape, put the ſtouteſt men to the Sword, but preſerved <hi>Myantonomy</hi> till they returned to <hi>Stoneing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> where our <hi>Indian</hi> friends and moſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Soldiers, declaring to the Commanders their fear, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhould upon conditions releaſe him, and that then he would (though the <hi>Engliſh</hi> might have peace with him) be very pernicious to thoſe <hi>Indians</hi> that now aſſiſted us, the ſaid <hi>Indians</hi> (on theſe conſiderations, and the miſchiefs and murthers he had done, during this war) permitted to put him to death; and that all might ſhare in the glory of deſtroying ſo great a Prince, and come under the obligation of fidelity each to other, the <hi>Pequods</hi> ſhot him, the <hi>Mohegins</hi> cut off his head, and quartered his body, and the <hi>Ninnicrofts</hi> men made the fire, and burned his quarters; and as a token of their love and fidelity to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> preſented his head to the Council at <hi>Hartford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:50660:7"/>About the ſame time we had information from an <hi>Indian</hi> ſpy taken by our Army, that the Enemy had a deſigne on the next day to fall upon the Gariſon, and ſome few houſes that remained at <hi>Marleborough,</hi> to revenge the death of one of their eminent men that was ſlain when they were laſt there (his name being concealed): Upon which our Major Generall, who was ſent to meet Major <hi>Savage,</hi> and accompany him and his Forces to <hi>Boſton,</hi> commanded Capt. <hi>Moſeley</hi> and another Captain with their Companies thither, to abide and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the Enemy 24 hours, but they not coming in that time, our ſaid Forces were called home and disbanded, to the diſſatisfaction of ſome people who thereupon feared the like fatall conſequences, that but a little before attended the like occaſion. Nor were ſuch their apprehenſions vain, for within 4 days afterwards news arrived at <hi>Boſton,</hi> that all the houſes at the ſaid Town of <hi>Marleborough</hi> (except the Gariſon) were deſtroied.</p>
            <p>April 20. Capt. <hi>Wadſworth</hi> of <hi>Dorcheſter,</hi> being deſigned with an 100. men to repair to <hi>Marlborough,</hi> to ſtrengthen the Gariſon, and remove the goods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there, did accordingly this Evening march with about 70 men from <hi>Sudbury,</hi> the reſt of his men not appearing; The Enemy who were about a 1000 ſtrong lay near his paſſage, but kept themſelves undiſcovered, and permitted him to paſſe them in the night, but in the morning aſſaulted and burned moſt of the Houſes in <hi>Sudbury</hi> (ſave thoſe that were ingariſon'd:) Upon which the Town of <hi>Concord</hi> receiving the Alarm, 12 reſolute young men haſtened from thence to their Neighbours relief, but were way-laid, and 11. of them cut off; But by the time Capt. <hi>Wadſworth</hi> was come to <hi>Marlborough,</hi> the alarm and news of this diſaſter overtook him, and although he had marched all the day and night before, and his men much wearied, yet he haſtned back again and was accompanied by Capt. <hi>Brocklebank</hi> Commander of the Gariſon at <hi>Marlebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough,</hi> with what ſmall number he durſt ſpare out of his Gariſon, when they arrived within a mile and a half of <hi>Sudbury;</hi> The Enemy having hid themſelves behind the hills, ſent forth 2 or 3 to croſs the March of our forces, and being ſeen, to counterfeit themſelves affrighted, and fly, thereby to trapan our men into their ambuſcade, which miſchievous deſigne ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to their wiſhes; for our men purſuing them, and being not above 80 in number, and thoſe miſerably tired as well with tedious marches as for want of ſleep, were ſuddenly ſet upon, and on every ſide encompaſſed with the Enemy, being about a 1000. ſtrong; yet not at all diſmaied with their numbers, nor diſmal ſhouts, and horrid yellings, ours made a moſt couragious reſiſtance; and having gained the top of a hill, they from thence gallantly defended themſelves with the loſs of 5 men near 4 hours; The cowardly Savages diſheartned with the ſight of ſo many of their fellows ſlain in the firſt attacque, not daring to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture cloſe upon them, yet (that we may not think theſe barbarians alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unacquainted with ſtratagems, nor ſo ſilly as to neglect any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages,) at laſt they ſet the woods on fire to the windward of our men, which by reaſon of the winde blowing very hard and the graſs being exceeding dry, burnt with a terrible fierceneſs, and with the ſmoak and heat was like to choak them, ſo that being no longer able at once to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the approaching fire, and the cruel enemy, they were forced to quit that advantagious poſt in diſorder; which the <hi>Indians</hi> taking advantage of, came on upon them like ſo many tigers, and dulling their active ſwords
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50660:7"/>
with exceſſive numbers, obtained the diſhonour of a victory, our two Captains, after incomparable proofs of their reſolution and gallantry, being ſlain upon the place; together with moſt of their men; but thoſe few that remained, eſcaped to a Mill, which they defended till night, when they were hapily reſcued by Capt. <hi>Prentice,</hi> who coming in the day haſtily, though ſomewhat too late to the relief of Capt. <hi>Wadſworth,</hi> having not aboue Six Troopers that were able to keep way with him: fell into a pound, or place near <hi>Sudbury</hi> Towns end, where all paſſages were ſtopt by the <hi>Indians;</hi> and had not Captain <hi>Cowell</hi> (who in his return from <hi>Quoboge</hi> had avoided the Common Rode providentially, at that inſtant come thither with about thirty Dragoons (who were forced to fight their way through) and two Files of men ſent from a Gariſon to ſecure ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſage, which the Enemy haſtned to ſtop againſt Captain <hi>Cowell,</hi> both the ſaid Captain <hi>Prentice</hi> and his men, and the remainder of the ſaid Captain <hi>Wadſworths</hi> men in the Mill, had been all kill'd or taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live: Nor did Captain <hi>Cowell</hi> loſe above ſix or ſeven of his men in this Engagement; But ſo inſolent were the <hi>Indians</hi> grown upon their firſt Succeſſe againſt Captain <hi>Wadſworth,</hi> that they ſent us word, to provide ſtore of good chear, for they intended to Dine with us upon the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction-Day.</p>
            <p>But for preventing any Danger that might happen on that Occaſion, the following Order was Printed and Publiſhed.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <head>At a Council held ar <hi>Boſton, April</hi> 21. 1676.</head>
                        <p>FOr the Prevention of ſuch Miſchiefs as may be deſigned by the Common Enemy, and the Securing of the ſeveral Plantations up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Day of Publike Election now drawing near;</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>It is Ordered,</hi> That the Committees of Militia in each Town, do take effectual Care that the Trained Soldiers be in Arms upon that Day, and keep Watch and Ward, with all dilligence, under the Command of one Commiſſion-Officer at leaſt, or ſome other meet Perſon where no Commiſſion-Officer is to be had; Which Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo employed for that Day in every Town, is alſo ſtrictly requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to forbid and prevent all rudeneſſe by Playing, Drinking, or otherwiſe; And for the better Execution of this Order, The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees of Militia aforeſaid ſhall take ſome meet courſe for the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Publiſhing the ſame to their ſeveral Towns; That ſuch of them as are Freemen, may (as many of them as may be) timely put in their Votes by Proxy, which for this extraordinary ſeaſon is moſt adviſable, and hereby Recommended to them to do; All Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and Inhabitants being hereby enjoyned and Commanded in all reſpects to yield Obedience accordingly.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>By the Council, <hi>Edward Rawſon,</hi> Secr.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:50660:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 26. Captain <hi>Hinskman</hi> having received Commiſſion and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, did then march for Major <hi>Wilberds</hi> Funerall (who died in his bed in peace, though God had honoured him with ſeverall ſignal Victories over our Enemys in war) to <hi>Charles</hi>-Town, and from thence to <hi>Concord,</hi> the place of Rendevouz. From Mr. <hi>Woodcocks</hi> Gariſon we hear, that himſelf and two of his Sons, and ſome other men being gone out to labour in the field were about this time ſurpriſed, one of his Sons and another man being killed, and himſelf and the other Son dangerouſly (though as it pleaſed God, not mortally) wounded, ſo that there were only five ſound perſons left to keep Gariſon, beſides the old woman and three daughters, and yet (through mercy) it has always held out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> the Firſt, Captain <hi>Denniſon</hi> with his Volunteers and <hi>Indians</hi> fell upon a Party of the Enemy, and killed Six and twenty of them, and took fifty Captives; Alſo we had advice, that the <hi>Pequods</hi> and other Friendly <hi>Indians,</hi> had carried many Priſoners to <hi>New London,</hi> that ſome had voluntarily ſurrendred themſelves to the Magiſtrates of <hi>Connecticot</hi>-Colony, and more came in from the <hi>Sachem</hi> of <hi>Penny-cook.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About a fortnight afterwards, the fore-mentioned Captain <hi>Turner,</hi> by Trade a Taylor, but one that for his Valour has left behinde him an Honourable Memory, hearing of the <hi>Indians</hi> being about Twenty miles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove them at <hi>Connecticot</hi> River; drew out a Party at <hi>Hadly</hi> and <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton,</hi> where there was a Garriſon; and marching all night, came upon them before day-break, they having no Centinels or Scouts abroad, as thinking themſelves ſecure, by reaſon of their remote diſtance from any of our Plantations; ours taking this advantage of their negligence, fell in amongſt them, and killed ſeveral hundreds of them upon the place, they being out of any poſture or order to make any formidable reſiſtance, though they were ſix times ſuperiour to us in number; But that which was almoſt as much, nay in ſome reſpect more conſiderable then their lives, we there deſtroied all their Ammunition and Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which we think they can hardly be ſo ſoon and eaſily recruited with, as poſſibly they may be with men: We likewiſe here demoliſht Two Forges they had to mend their Armes, took away all their mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialls and Tools, and drove many of them into the River, where they were drowned, and threw two great Piggs of Lead of theirs, (intended for making of bullets) into the ſaid River: But this great ſucceſſe was not altogether without its allay, as if Providence had deſigned to chec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer our joys and ſorrows; and leſt we ſhould ſacrifice to our own Nets, and ſay, Our own Arms or proweſſe hath done this, to permit the Enemy preſently after to take an advantage againſt us; For as our men were returning to <hi>Hadly</hi> in a dangerous Paſſe, which they were not ſufficiently aware of, the skulking <hi>Indians</hi> (out of the Woods) killed, at one Volley, the ſaid Captain, and Eight and Thirty of his men, but immediatly after they had diſcharged, they fled.</p>
            <p>In <hi>June</hi> Major <hi>Talkot</hi> ſlew and took captive Four and Twenty of the Enemies in one Weeks time, and alſo killed the Old Queen of <hi>Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganſet,</hi> and an arch Villain of their Party, that had been with them at the ſacking of <hi>Providence,</hi> famouſly known by the Name of <hi>Stone-wall</hi> or <hi>Stone-Layer John,</hi> for that being an active ingenious Fellow, he had learnt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50660:8"/>
the Maſons Trade, and was of great uſe to the <hi>Indians</hi> in building their Forts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Likewiſe <hi>Potucke</hi> the Great <hi>Indian</hi> Counſellour (a man conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering his Education, of a wonderfull ſubtlety) was brought Priſoner into <hi>Rhode-Iſland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>July</hi> we had very conſiderable Forces abroad, who took and killed above 200. of the barbarous bloudy <hi>Indians,</hi> and that cruell Infidel <hi>Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cham</hi> amongſt the reſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Squaw Sachem</hi> King <hi>Philips</hi> Siſter, who at firſt ſo much promoted this Warr, and was ſince by Treaty with <hi>Ninnicroft Sachem</hi> of the <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raganſets</hi> to be delivered up, hath lately ſurrendred her ſelf, and is come into the <hi>Plimmouth</hi> Army, having ſubmitted to the mercy of Major <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> who with a ſmall Party ſome time ſince ſeparated himſelf from the reſt of his <hi>Narraganſets,</hi> pretending (when he found they could not proſper) that he diſapproved of their doings, in breaking their Treaty with the Engliſh, hath likewiſe taken ſhelter under our Forces at <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neington,</hi> to ſecure his Life at preſent; For not only thoſe of his men that continue in Rebellion ſtill, but likewiſe thoſe that formerly ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred themſelves to us, threaten to cut off his Head; the firſt pretending that by his treacherous Councils he drew them into this Warr, and then baſely deſerted them; and the ſecond, charging him as a Traytor and Truce-breaker to the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> Thus abominable is Treachery and Violation of ones Faith even amongſt the moſt barbarous and ſavage In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Philip</hi> and ſome of theſe Northern <hi>Indians</hi> being wandred up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Albany,</hi> the <hi>Mohucks</hi> marched out very ſtrong, in a warlike po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture upon them, putting them to flight, and purſuing them as far as <hi>Hoſſicke</hi>-River, which is about two days march from the Eaſt-ſide of <hi>Hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi>-River to the N.E. killing diverſe, and bringing away ſome priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners with great pride and triumph, which ill ſucceſſe on that ſide where they did not expect any enemy, having lately endeavoured to make up the ancient animofities, did very much daunt and diſcourage the ſaid Northern <hi>Indians,</hi> ſo that ſome hundreds came in and ſubmitted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at <hi>Plimmouth</hi>-Colony; and <hi>Philip</hi> himſelf is run skul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away into ſome <hi>Swamp,</hi> with not above ten men attending him; Nor doubt we ſhortly to have a good account given of that Prime In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiary, there being ſeverall of our Troops daily abroad in Queſt of him.</p>
            <p>It is Computed by moſt Judicious men, That the <hi>Indians</hi> that were killed, taken, ſent away, and now of late come in by way of ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, cannot in all (Men, Women and Children) amount to fewer then Six Thouſand, beſides vaſt quantities of their Corn, Houſes, Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and other Neceſſaries, without which they cannot long ſubſiſt, in Hoſtility taken and deſtroyed.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A True but Brief Account of our Loſſes ſuſtained ſince this Cruel and Miſchievous War began, take as follows.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>In <hi>Narraganſet</hi> not One Houſe left ſtanding.</item>
                  <item>At <hi>Warwick</hi> but One.</item>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:50660:9"/>
                  <item>At <hi>Providence</hi> not above Three.</item>
                  <item>At <hi>Potuxit</hi> none left.</item>
                  <item>Very Few at <hi>Seaconicke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>At <hi>Swanſey</hi> two at moſt.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Marlborough</hi> wholly laid aſhes, except two or three Houſes.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Grantham</hi> and <hi>Naſhaway</hi> all ruined but one houſe or two.</item>
                  <item>Many Houſes burnt at <hi>Springfield, Scituate, Lancaſter, Brookefield,</hi> and <hi>Northampton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The greateſt part of <hi>Rehoboth</hi> and <hi>Taunton</hi> deſtroyed.</item>
                  <item>Great ſpoil made at <hi>Hadley, Hatfield</hi> and <hi>Chelmsford.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Deerfield</hi> wholly, and <hi>Weſtfield</hi> much ruined.</item>
                  <item>At <hi>Sudbury</hi> many Houſes burnt, and ſome at <hi>Hingham, Weymouth,</hi> and <hi>Braintree.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Beſides particular Farms and Plantations, a great Number, not to be reckoned up, wholly laid waſte, or very much damnified.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And as to Perſons, it is generally thought, that of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there hath been Loſt in all (Men, Women and Children) above Eight Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſince the War began; of whom many have been deſtroyed with exquiſite Torments and moſt inhumane barbarities; the Heathen rarely giving Quarter to thoſe that they take, but if they were Women, they firſt forced them to ſatisfie their filthy luſts, and then murthered them, either cutting off the head, ripping open the Belly, or skulping the head of skin and hair, and hanging them up as Trophees; wearing mens fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers as bracelets about their Necks, and ſtripes of their skins which they dreſſe for Belts: They knockt one Youth of the Head, and laying him for dead, they flead (or skulp'd) his head of skin and hair; After which the boy wonderfully revived, and is now recovered, only he hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the dry Skull, neither skin nor hair on his head; Nor have our Cattle eſcaped the Cruelty of theſe worſe then brute and ſavage beaſts; For what cattle they took they ſeldom killed outright; or if they did would eat but little of the fleſh, but rather cut their bellies, and letting them go ſeverall days, trailing their guts after them, putting out their eyes, or cutting off one leg, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But to reckon up all their Cruelties, would be no leſſe burthenſome to compaſſionate Chriſtians ears, then too tedious for a Letter, which is already ſwelled too big; and therefore I think it now high time to conclude, with hearty thanks to Almighty God for our late ſucceſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this bloudy Enemy, whereby though not wholly freed from ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of future dangers, yet we have grounds to hope, that their fury is much quaſht and abated, ſo that (if our ſins obſtruct not ſo great a bleſſing) we may ſhortly once again ſee peace and ſafety reſtored to our (lately diſconſolate) habitations in this Wilderneſs; For which, as I doubt not of the concurence of yours and all good Chriſtians prayers, ſo I ſhall not fail to recommend you and yours to the ſame Almighty protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and with my hearty reſpects preſented, remain,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your affectionate Friend and Servant, <hi>N. S.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:50660:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
